Viruses, bacteria, alien life forms,
they can invade your body through your
nose, your mouth. Ridley has experienced
that one. A cut to your skin, entry
through your eyes, and believe it or
not, your intestines, too, which isn't
often considered, but is a major
battleground between your body and a
variety of illness spawning microbes. If
your intestinal barrier that separates
these microbes from our bloodstream
isn't maintained, we can get some nasty
consequences. Just ask people dealing
with ulcerative colitis, irritable bowel
syndrome, and other gut related issues.
And even when harmful microbes get past
our physical barriers, how our immune
system responds is also critical because
an overreaction like me screaming at a
mouse can cause pain and damage to our
supposedly healthy gut. But an
underreaction like the one that I have
when people who say mean things about me
in the comments and across social media
is also a risk. So, how do we maintain a
tight balance that allows our body to
respond swiftly and accurately like John
Wick without overdoing it? Like John
Wick, dude really loved his dog. I guess
I can't blame him. Well, there's a
nutrient that does exactly that as I'll
show you. This nutrient affects popular
immune cells called macrofasages. These
immune cells are found in the lamina
propaya which is an area right behind
that physical barrier of epithelial
cells that make up our intestinal tract.
It's filled with loose connective tissue
and offers a structure to the
intestines. However, it's also where an
army of immune cells wait as a second
line of defense. So, what's the nutrient
and how exactly does it improve our
immune system and gut? Well, as you see
by the title here, it's a fat called
butyrate. And ironically, you can
stimulate your body to produce it, but
not necessarily by eating it. We'll get
into how, but for now, let's look at how
it affects your immune system's
precision and deadliness to pathogens.
Researchers took human macrofasages and
exposed them to different harmful
bacteria. Think salmonella, certain
ecoli, and the like. They then simply
expose the cells to butyrate or not the
control condition here. Here we're
looking at the number of Salammonella
bacteria still present after infection.
The red condition is the butyrate
treated macrofasages. So the lower the
dots, the fewer the remaining bacteria.
For those in immunology, this is a genty
assay. I realize there's more to the
experimental design, but we'll have to
keep it simple this time. The right side
is the literal image of the bacterial
colonies. Clearly there are fewer. So
butyrate clearly improves macrofase
ability to kill bacteria. So pathogens.
As an FYI, this was also repeated with
multiple other bacteria and the results
were the exact same. But how does it do
that? And even more importantly, does it
increase the deadliness of these cells
at the expense of more inflammation in
the area, which we don't want. Remember,
that's like me overreacting to a mouse.
Too much screeching for nothing. Well,
we get clues by looking at data like
this. Here the researchers are measuring
the acidity around the macrofasages that
tells us that if the cells are more or
less glycolytic, meaning that the cells
are using sugar glucose as their fuel
source. One of the products of some of
the sugar metabolism is an increase in
acidity. I won't explain this experiment
in extreme detail. Just note that if the
lines go up, there's more acidity,
therefore more sugar metabolism. But as
you can see, the butyrate condition
offers a reduction in acidity,
indicating that the cells are likely
relying more on fat metabolism for
energy. That makes more sense
considering butyrate is a fat, but
that's not really the whole story here.
Not only does butyrate change the
metabolism of cells, which if you look
in the literature, a less glycolytic,
more fat-based metabolism for immune
cells typically means that they are
anti-inflammatory or pro-resolution or
repair state. I want to be clear that's
a generalization, but it's been true
across a lot of literature, even if
there's more complexity and exceptions
to the matter that we can't get into
now. So, not only does butyrate change
the metabolism of these key immune
cells, but it changes the signaling
inside the cells in a critical and
amazing way. If you're in the field or
an enthusiast, you likely know about a
master enzyme inside your cells called
EMPK. This enzyme is critical for
sending many signals across the cell.
But critically, it plays a big role in
something called autophagy. You might
have heard of this uh buzzword called
autophagy, which isn't actually a
buzzword in the scientific world. It
just has been hijacked across social
media. Anyway, autophagy is a process
where your cells eat parts of
themselves. It's often called a
selfcleaning process. Get it? Cell
instead of self.
If your mouth didn't even twitch up, I
understand. Uh the point being that
autophagy cleans out and destroys
different elements within the cell and
EMPK this enzyme plays a critical role
in activating it but also activating
something called xenophagy. Autophagy
and xenophagy differ in that autophagy
eliminates and cleans up proteins and
whole organels from the cell. But
xenophagi is triggered when a pathogen
has been absorbed into the cell and
escapes or damages its prison. When
immune cells take up pathogens, it's
like they consume them, encasing them in
a prison called a vacule. This process
is called fagocytosis. However, some
pathogens have tools, molecules to
escape the vacule called a secretion
system. In some instances, the vacule
ruptures while the bacterium is inside
the macroofase, leading to the bacterium
running around inside the cell. Think of
it like something foreign being inside
of your rib cage. There are entirely too
many alien references. Anyway, this is
where something like xenophagi might be
called upon to recapture the bacterium
and lead it to the gallows, hence the
name xeno for foreign. So how does
butyrate play into this? Well, here
we're looking at autophagy xenophagi
activating master enzymek.
And we can clearly see that the enzyme
concentration is greater with butyrate.
However, downstream measures we can also
see it activates proteins responsible
for encapsulating and destroying these
foreign bodies. Here on the left we have
the quantification with the with and
without salmonella infection. The
infection itself independent of butyrate
increases LC32 levels which is a protein
that sits on the vesicle that captures
the pathogen. It's used as a marker of
mature versions of these destructive
vesicles called autotolys or in this
case a xenolosome.
Once butyrate is added, we can see that
the levels are even greater and we can
see images of what's happening inside
the macrofasages too on the right. The
green is a fluorescent tag applied to
cella the infecting bacteria and LC3 is
a protein that is recognized on the
destructive vesicles. And the blue stain
there is simply to identify the
macrofasages by their nuclei. Not
something that we need to worry about.
In the control, we clearly see
salmonella inside the cell. We can't see
if they're free or still stuck in the
original vacule. But on the right side
with butyrate, we see a lot more of this
xenopagic activity evidenced by more LC3
present, indicating that the cells are
destroying the infection, which is
pretty neat, right? But while the
precision and pathogen destructive
ability of the macrofasages is improved,
does this also mean that there's an
increase in the overall inflammation to
achieve these effects? Well, if you look
at the supplemental data in this study,
we're looking at pro-inflammatory
cytoine levels. So both interlucan one
and tumor necrosis factor alpha, there
are molecules secreted by cells that
stimulate the immune system, greater
inflammation. So while we do see
increases in both molecules when the
infection is added indicated by the plus
symbol there, the key answer to our
question lies in the comparison between
the control infection and the butyrate
infection conditions. The butyrate
condition does not show a greater
inflammation signal even though it is
far better at killing the infection.
That's pretty damn fascinating. To be
clear, I would want to see more evidence
like an actual cellular behavior like
migration, amounts of cells and so on.
But this is a good start. In fact, if we
look at a TSN plot or a teddistributed
stochastic neighbor embedding plot, I
understood the word neighbor and then my
brain saw all the colors and reacted
like those minions from those movies.
Anyway, this tells us that the
difference in the genes that are red or
expressed between the butyrate treated
cells and the nonbutyrate treated immune
cells. Each dot is a cell and the red
cluster corresponds to an important
aspect of the xenophagi that we
discussed earlier. Same with the green
cluster including antimicrobial genes.
Meanwhile, the orange and blue cluster
indicate the more traditional pathway of
fagocytosis and pro-inflammatory
pathway. In the end, the interpretation
here is that while yes, the immune cells
are upregulating their ability to
destroy microbes like bacteria, they are
not necessarily overstimulating to a
pro-inflammatory state. There's some
limitations to the interpretations of
these data as this is only from two
samples and although it looks like a lot
of cells, it should still be interpreted
with caution. Plus, assigning labels to
clusters is inherently biased. Still,
it's just one piece of multiple
indicating a through line to an
increased precision of immune cells
without an overburdening increase in
inflammation. The way I think about it,
and excuse me for this side thought and
its revealing nature is the cells are a
lot like a Halo player called Precision
who is extremely precise in his shots.
If you didn't know, I'm an uber fan of
the Halo series, books, games, whatever.
And there are pro players that have
unique names. Precision is one of them.
accurate without undue damage to his
teammates. Much like the macrofasages
impacted by butyrate. Okay, before we
get into how to raise our butyrate
levels in our body, there are other fats
that also have these immune precision
effects. And there's a lot more on
exactly how butyrate communicates with
our cells. Oh, and the details on
butyrate supplementation if you wanted
to go down that route and bypass what
we're about to go over. Not to mention
an added advantage of supplementation
for some people. I'll be covering that
in the extended version of the video
that you're watching. It's part of my
premium research platform and community
called the Physionic Insiders. You also
get an accompanying article uh articles
released every week along with videos
for the insiders and I also do regular
live sessions to discuss these topics in
more depth with the insider community
plus a private podcast and so much more.
It's a steal if you're looking to learn
everything there is on the topics that
we go over. Plus, I'm able to answer a
lot more questions in the insider
community because it's a much more
intimate uh area than social media.
Anyway, I don't want to belabor the
point further. If you're interested in
accessing all that, just to join the
Physiotic Insiders, the link is in the
description. Well, that said, how do we
increase butyrate? Surprisingly, it's
not a fat that we generally consume in
its fat form. Although some foods
contain it, like butter, but we actually
rely on our microbiome, the healthy
bacteria in our intestines to take up
precursor nutrients that we consume and
convert them to their purest form of
butyrate, which is then absorbed into
the bloodstream and affects our immune
cells as described. Those precursor
nutrients are dietary fiber. That's
right, fiber like the one found in
broccoli. Ew, I know. Lentils,
chickpeas, beans, oats, barley, cooked
and cooled potatoes, psyllium husk, and
plenty of other dietary fiber sources.
So, all in all, what do we make of these
data? Maybe a few words of caution.
Well, the usual cautions belong here.
We've been using cells, not full-on
human beings. In addition, in relation
to fiber, some people experience worse
gut health from fiber consumption. I'm
only pointing that out because we're
talking about uh the average situation.
So, possibly even some gap gut
pathologies related to inflammation, but
there's no doubt that some people
experience issues with too much fiber
consumption. But on average, these
results are somewhat substantiated in
other studies, including human trials,
indicating improved gut health and
symptoms with fiber consumption. The
same is true for reduced general
inflammation as well. So while I
wouldn't jump to any applicable
conclusions if we only had this one
study, we fortunately don't have just
this one study. So everything
considered, where does that leave us?
Well, it tells us that the shortchain
fat butyrate is a player in improving
macrofase or immune cells ability to
eliminate infectious microbes by at
least one way increasing xenophagy. This
could be one mechanism by which
nutrients like dietary fiber are able to
improve gut health on average. And while
the overall effect is confirmed in some
of the human trials, more research is
necessary to confirm some of the
experiments that we went over. But you
know, butyrate does much more than help
your immune system. In fact, it can
flood into cancer cells and cause some
wild yet nuanced effects. Check it out
right here. Wouldn't it be fun if uh
people who fell asleep at the beginning
of the video woke up and we were talking
about something completely different?
Anyway, like I was saying, socks cause
an irreparable foot fungus that make you
grow bald.